Finding Aid for Will E. Hampton Papers, 1839-1959 [microform]
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Will E. Hampton papers [microform] 1839-1959
Hampton, Will E., 1864-1959.
2 microfilms
851396 Aa 2
Mayor of Charlevoix, Michigan, editor and publisher of the Charlevoix Courier 1890-1920, secretary of the state lodge of the Knights of Pythias; correspondence and miscellaneous paper relating to the Knights of Pythias, and Civil War reminiscences and letters of his father, Carlos Hampton, surgeon with the Michigan 4th Infantry and his mother's account of her civil war experiences in Hunt County, Texas.
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection (Accession No. 3652 ) was obtained through Victor Hampton in 1960.
The collection is open for research. Access to the original papers is restricted. Researchers must use microfilm copy.
The originals of the Hampton papers are held by the Bentley Historical Library.
Will E. Hampton was editor and publisher of the Charlevoix Courier, 1890-1910, and Grand Secretary of the Knights of Pythias, 1904-1944. He was twice elected mayor of Charlevoix, Michigan and also served on the city council and school board.
Hampton was born May 14, 1864 at Hudson, Michigan to Dr. Carlos E. Hampton (1821-1893) and Cornelia C. Hampton (1825-1903). His father served as surgeon of the 4th Michigan Infantry during the Civil War. His mother was the daughter of Capt. Apollos Drown who fought in the Blackhawk War in Michigan. Hampton moved with his family to Harbor Springs in 1875. Three years later he began working for his brother Charles at the Spring Harbor Independent, working his way up from printer's devil to editor. In 1890 Hampton moved to Charlevoix and became editor and publisher of the Charlevoix Courier. He retired from the newspaper business in 1920 and moved to Ann Arbor, Michigan where he devoted himself to the activities of the Knights of Pythias fraternal lodge.
In 1904 Hampton was elected Grand Chancellor of the Knights of Pythias and in 1906 was named the lodge's Grand Secretary, a post he held until 1944. He was also editor of the official publication of the Knights.
Hampton was first married to Jennie E. Lathrop, who died in 1920. He then married Jennie E. Crouter in 1922. He had three sons, Charles H., Victor H. and Will Jr. Will Hampton Sr. died January 18, 1959 at the County Convalescent Home near Milford, Michigan.
The Will Hampton papers consist of correspondence, poetry, speeches, and historical reminiscences of Will Hampton as well as poetry and reminiscences of his mother Cornelia C. Hampton and correspondence of his father Carlos D. Hampton relating to his service in the Civil War.
The collection is arranged in three series: Cornelia C. Hampton, Carlos D. Hampton and Will E. Hampton.
The Cornelia C. Hampton series includes a typescript reminiscence, " A Story of the South During the Civil War Days and the Harrowing Experiences of Mrs. C.C. Hampton, Mother of Will E. Hampton and the Outrages Suffered at Hands of the Texas Secessionists." The story, recorded by Will Hampton based on recollections of his mother, describes the experiences of Carlos and Cornelia Hampton in Hunt County, Texas during the years 1858-1862, the pressures on Dr. Hampton to enlist in the Confederate army and Cornelia's journey back to Michigan in 1862. There are also three poems by Cornelia Hampton.
The Carlos D. Hampton series consists of correspondence and miscellaneous papers, 1862-1898 principally relating to his service as surgeon in the Michigan 4th Infantry, during the Civil War and efforts to obtain a pension and benefits after the war.
The Will E. Hampton series consists of correspondence and miscellaneous papers, 1984-1954, poetry and other writing, historical reminiscences, photographs and three scrapbooks. The correspondence and miscellaneous papers, arranged chronologically, include material relating to the Knights of Pythias, family history, Hampton's research on the history o f Charlevoix, Spring Harbor and the Native American tribes of Michigan.
There are two folders of poetry by Will Hampton and the scrapbooks contain additional poems by him as well as verse clipped from magazines and other sources. The photographs consist of several family portraits and a picture of the Harbor Springs Cornet Band, ca. 1881. There are some photos in the scrapbooks as well.
Subject Terms
Hampton, Will E., 1864-1959.; Hampton, Carlos D.; Hampton, Corneia C.; Knights of Pythias.; United States. Army. Michigan Regiment, 4th (1862-1866); Indians of North America.; Physicians--Michigan.; Women--History.; Charlevoix (Mich.); Harbor Springs (Mich.); Texas.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Medical care.
Form and Genre Terms
Poetry.
Contributors
Hampton, Carlos D.; Hampton, Cornelia D.
- Cornelia C. Hampton
  - Reminiscences by Mrs. C. C. Hampton of Texas in the Civil War (Reel 1)
  - Poetry and Letters 1839-circa 1860 (Reel 1)
- Carlos D. Hampton 1862-1898
  - Correspondence and miscellaneous 1862-1898
    - 1862-1898 (Reel 1)
    - 1865 (Reel 1)
    - 1866 (Reel 1)
    - 1867-1898 (Reel 1)
- Will E. Hampton 1894-1959
  - Correspondence and Miscellaneous papers 1894-1959
    - 1894-1909 (Reel 1)
    - 1910-1935 (Reel 1)
    - 1936-1953 (Reel 1)
    - 1954-August 1955 (Reel 1)
    - September 1955-May 1956 (Reel 1)
    - June 1956-July 1956 (Reel 1)
    - August 1956-December 1956 (Reel 1)
    - 1957-1959 (Reel 1)
  - Newspaper Obituaries 1959 (Reel 1)
  - Memoirs of Charlevoix (Reel 2)
  - Poems, 2 folders (Reel 2)
  - Undated speeches and miscellaneous (Reel 2)
  - Miscellaneous papers dealing with Indians (Reel 2)
  - Memoirs of Harbor Springs (Reel 2)
  - Photographs (Reel 2)
  - Scrapbooks
    - Verses by Will Hampton (Reel 2)
    - Collected Verse and Commonplace Book (Reel 2)
    - Photographs, Clippings and Verse (Reel 2)